A Finding Aid to the Raphael Soyer Papers, 1933-1989, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1940-1988; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
  - Correspondence, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Undated Correspondence, A-B, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Undated Correspondence, C-G, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Undated Correspondence, H-K, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Undated Correspondence, L-O, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Undated Correspondence, P-R, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Undated Correspondence, S-Z, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1940-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters Addressed to Reality, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters Addressed to Reality, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters Addressed to Reality, Undated Letters, circa 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Writings & Notes, circa 1946-1987; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2-3; 1.5 linear feet)
  The Writings and Notes series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Writings and Notes by Soyer, circa 1946-1987
  Subseries 3.2: Writings & Notes by Others, 1953-1984
  Scope and Contents
  Writings and notes by Soyer include several drafts and notes for his four published books as well as draft essays, lectures, and articles. Writings by others include essays and articles by artists and art scholars.
  - Writings & Notes by Soyer, circa 1946-1987; 3.1; Archival Resource Key
    Among the writings and notes by Soyer are his writings about artists, primarily draft essays for articles and introductions of exhibition catalogs. Artists written about include Benny Andrews, Jacques Lipchitz, Alice Neel, and others. Additional writings by Soyer include drafts of book reviews, and drafts of articles, essays, and lectures about his life, his artwork, and the social realism art movement.
    Also found are drafts, notes, typescripts, journals, and galley proofs for Soyer's four published books A Painter's Pilgrimage (1962), Homage to Thomas Eakins (1966), Self-Revealment: a Memoir (1969), and Diary of an Artist (1977). Also among the writings by Soyer are 13 of his engagement calendars and other miscellaneous notes.
    Most of Soyer's writings have been scanned, except for repetitive drafts and incomplete repetitive manuscripts and galley proofs of his published books. Early drafts of published books have been scanned.
    - Writings about Artists, circa 1950-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Book Reviews, circa 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Articles, Essays, and Lectures, circa 1946-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Articles, Essays, and Lectures, circa 1946-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Material concerning Diary of an Artist, 1965-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Material concerning Diary of an Artist, 1965-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Material concerning Diary of an Artist, 1965-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Travel Journal and Manuscripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Incomplete Draft Typescripts for Homage to Eakins, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24-28)
    - Notes for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Notes for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Notes for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Notes for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Incomplete Draft Typescripts for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33-38)
    - Galley Proofs for A Painter's Pilgrimage, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Notes and Manuscripts for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Notes and Manuscripts for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Notes and Manuscripts for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Notes and Manuscripts for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Early Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Early Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Early Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Second Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47-52)
    - Second Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Third Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Third Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Third Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Third Draft for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Galley Proofs for Self Revealment, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1967; 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1981, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Engagement Calendars, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1950s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writings & Notes by Others, 1953-1984; 3.2; Archival Resource Key
    Writings and notes by others include various draft typescripts of essays, articles, and one dissertation about various artists and art movements written by art scholars. Most of these essays appear to have been sent to Soyer for his review and opinion. Also found are a few short essays about Soyer. Additional items of note are draft articles written by artists for Reality magazine, for which Soyer was an editor.
    This subseries has not been scanned.
    - John Baker, "Guy Pene Du Bois on Realism,", 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - William Benton, "Reginald Marsh as I Remember Him,", circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - William H. Gerdts, "Werner Groshans and His Art,", circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Patricia Hills, Review of Serge Guilbaut, How New York Stole The Idea of Modern Art, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Patricia Hills, "The Socially Concerned Painters of the 1930s,", 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Patricia Hills, "Social Concern and Urban Realism: American Painting in the 1930s,", 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Norma Nichols, Dissertation, The Mirrors of Eve: Changing Images of Women in American Art, 1670-1980, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - Frances M. Wilson, Essay about Soyer's Homage to Thomas Eakins, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Writings about Soyer, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Articles & Notes for Reality, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Articles & Notes for Reality, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Poetry, 1958-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1954, circa 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Legal & Financial Records, 1959-1988; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scattered legal and financial records include two account books, bank statements, receipts, and invoices. Documents related to the publishing of Soyer's books include contracts with the publishers and royalty statements. Additional items found here are consignment lists and loan agreements with art museums and galleries for the exhibition of his work.
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder. Account books, bank statements, and receipts and invoices have not been scanned.
  - Account Books, 1962-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Bank Statements, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Consignment Lists & Loan Agreements, 1962-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Consignment Lists & Loan Agreements, 1980-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Contracts, 1959-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Contracts, 1976-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Leases, 1966-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Receipts & Invoices, 1964, 1970-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Royalty Statements, 1968-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, 1933-1989; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Box 3-4; 0.3 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of catalogs and announcements for exhibitions of Raphael Soyer's artwork and the artwork of others; numerous news clippings about Soyer, his exhibitions, publication of his books, and about realist painters; and a few articles written by Soyer. Other scattered items include brochures and press releases about art events, page proofs for Soyer's writings, and reproductions of his artwork. There are three issues of the journal Reality, of which Soyer was an editor.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned, except for a few extant brochures, entire magazines, scattered page proofs, and reproductions of artwork by Soyer and others.
  - Catalogs & Exhibition Announcements, 1941-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1933-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1948-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Clippings, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Clippings, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Clippings, 1973-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Clippings, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1985-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Undated Clippings, circa 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Booklet, "The Germans Got Madder and Madder" (Illustrated by Soyer), 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Brochures, 1944-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Business Cards, circa 1950-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Magazines, 1976, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Page Proofs, Raphael Soyer: Life Drawings and Portraits, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Page Proofs, Miscellaneous, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Press Releases, 1954, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reality Journal, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Soyer, circa 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, circa 1950s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Photographs, circa 1953-1987; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (Box 5, OV 6; 0.5 linear feet)
  Photographs depict Soyer painting portraits and drawing in his studio, with his wife Rebecca and with unidentified friends, with fellow artist Jose De Creeft after painting De Creeft's portrait, with his friend Isaac Bashevis Singer, and in the process of painting a portrait of Gross and his wife. Photographs of other artists include Chaim Gross, Edward Hopper, Joseph Floch, and Moses Soyer.
  Also found are photographs of art events, including gallery receptions, many of which are unidentified and undated. Many of the photographs of gallery receptions depict Soyer with artists including Jose De Creeft, Chaim Gross, Rudolf Baranik, David Burliuk, R. B. Kitaj, Leon Kroll, Jacob Lawrence, Jack Levine, Reuben Nakian, Alice Neel, and others. Also found are a few photographs of Soyer's artwork and artwork by others.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety, except for photographs of artwork by Soyer and others. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer in His Studio, 1969-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key; (Oversized photographs housed in OV 6) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Wife Rebecca & Friends, 1964-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Jose De Creeft, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer with Isaac Singer, circa early 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photograph of Joseph Floch, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (Housed in OV 6) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Chaim Gross, 1974-1982; Archival Resource Key; (Oversized photographs housed in OV 6) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Edward Hopper, circa 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Moses Soyer, circa early 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Photograph of Model, Eliza, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Raphael Soyer at Unidentifed Conference, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Presentation of Soyer's Portrait of Golda Meir to National Portrait Gallery, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Reception for Isaac Singer, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Birthday Party for Soyer (possibly at Hirshhorn Museum), circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Associated American Artists Galleries, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception (possibly at the Whitney Museum), 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception (possibly at the Forum Gallery), circa early 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Gallery Receptions, Early 1970s-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Gallery Receptions, Early 1970s-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Hirshhorn Gallery, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Gallery Reception, Forum Gallery, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Photograph of Unidentified People, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Gallery Installations, 1966, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Works by Raphael Soyer, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Works by Others, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Oversize Photographs of Raphael Soyer in His Studio, 1975-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key; (Scanned with Box 5, F1) (Box OV 6)
  - Oversize Photograph of Joseph Floch, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; (Scanned with Box 5, F5) (Box OV 6)
  - Oversize Photograph of Chaim Gross, 1974-1982; Archival Resource Key; (Scanned with Box 5, F6) (Box OV 6)
- Artwork, 1968, undated; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; (Box 5; 2 folders)
  Artwork found in this collection includes one undated pencil sketch by an unidentified artist and a facsimile of a 1968 sketchbook belonging to Raphael Soyer which documents his time traveling through Europe. This facsimile was produced by the Forum Gallery as a limited edition in 1968.
  - Sketch, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Raphael Soyer: A 1968 Sketchbook (Facsimile), Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 26)